Fletcher School Records UA015
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Fletcher program theses, 1981 -- 2015; UA015.012; 286 Digital Object(s); 1 Volumes
  - To what extent will the Panama Canal expansion lower transportation costs and enhance the competitiveness of exports from the United States?, 2013-04; UA015.012.081.00007; Metcalf, Shelton D.; The Panama Canal expansion plan, on pace to be completed in 2015, has the potential to alter international shipping routes. The $5.2 billion infrastructure project calls for building a third channel that will accommodate post-Panamax vessels, which will double the capacity limits for the canal. Additionally, some specialized vessels will be able to use the Canal that previously could not. As a result, exporters, logistics experts, port authorities, vessel operators, and many others are eagerly anticipating its completion. For the United States, the canal expansion is expected to benefit trade between the U.S. Gulf Coast and East Coast and Asian markets because using the canal significantly shortens the distance and transit time between these two locations. The expansion also permits the use of larger vessels that take advantage of economies of scale. In short, the improved canal is believed to reduce transportation costs for U.S. exports using this route, making U.S. export goods more competitive on the international market. However, this outcome is not assured for many reasons. First, other shipping routes have advantages that will compete with the Panama Canal. The main, competing routes from the U.S. Gulf to Asia are through the Suez Canal and around the Cape of Good Hope (South Africa). Second, many U.S. and Asian ports have draft limitations that exclude larger vessels from entering their harbors. Any increase in these ports drafts will take time and large financial investments. Third, the possibility of longer average transit times could counteract the benefits of the Panama Canal. Therefore, it is inconclusive at this point whether the expanded Panama Canal will be better than the alternatives and furthermore, whether it will have a positive impact on U.S. export competitiveness. Additionally, a key factor influencing U.S. export competitiveness via the Panama Canal expansion is the Canal toll rates. The Panama Canal Authority is keen to recoup its investment costs from the expansion project, and higher toll rates are expected. However, it is unknown by how much, or if at all, the rates will rise. To assess the impact of future Panama Canal on U.S. exports, this paper will first evaluate the transportation costs for select U.S. exports using the Panama Canal (based on its current toll rates) and compare them against the transportation costs using the Suez Canal and Cape of Good Hope routes. Second, it will conduct a sensitivity analysis test that compares the derived transportation costs for each U.S. export under different Panama Canal toll fee scenarios. This test will expose how sensitive transportation costs are for each good examined to canal rates vis-a-vis alternative shipping routes.
    Panama Canal (Panama); MALD thesis; Transportation--Cost of operation
  - Reparations for Child Victims of Armed Conflict: Responding to the Rights and Needs of Children in Transitional Justice, 2013-05; UA015.012.081.00008; Miano, Sarah M.; Modern warfare disproportionately affects children caught in the midst of complex and persistent conflict. Harm against young people, however, is not merely an unfortunate byproduct of war. Rather, children are frequently targeted in serious crimes under human rights and humanitarian law, including killing, sexual violence, recruitment and use in armed forces or groups, maiming, torture, and denial of basic services, to name a few. Unfortunately, children's roles as political, economic, and social actors are often undervalued, and their experiences during war are consequently deprioritized on post-conflict agendas. Yet, children are rights-holders and agents of social transformation, and processes seeking justice for victims of armed conflict are remiss to ignore this significant group. This paper explores the potentially meaningful role reparations processes and outcomes can play in facilitating justice for children victimized through serious crimes during armed conflict. Part 1 reviews the transitional justice framework, focusing on existing legal and normative guidance on reparations. This section also introduces children's rights principles, including non-discrimination, best interests, and evolving capacities of the child, which are applied throughout the analysis to ensure children's needs, rights, and protection are prioritized. Part 2 looks at children's experiences of war and the long-term and immediate impact of crimes on their lives, focusing on attributes of age, gender, and cultural context of the child. Parts 3 and 4 utilize the lenses of children's rights principles and attributes to examine the potential for child-sensitive and child-just processes and outcomes of reparation. Ultimately, this paper seeks to fill a gap in literature for approaching reparations for child victims of armed conflict rooted in their experience of war and the impact of harms on their lives.
    MALD thesis; Children's rights--Reparations; Transitional justice; War reparations
  - State Manipulation of NGOs: Government-Civil Society Relations in Egypt, 2013-03; UA015.012.081.00009; Pollock, John P.; Egypt has a large and vibrant NGO sector, yet it also has restrictive laws governing NGOs, and the government has frequently cracked down on the sector, both before and after the 25 January Revolution. What explains the size and vibrancy of Egyptian civil society in the face of this repression? After exploring the nature of the NGO sector in Egypt and the government's tools for constraining NGOs, this paper will evaluate possible answers to this question. Internal and external pressures on the Egyptian government as well as a lack of state capacity for repression might explain the size of the NGO sector. However, this paper concludes that the Egyptian government has intentionally promoted the growth of the NGO sector, while using the state's coercive power to influence these organizations. By both promoting and manipulating NGOs, the state has been able to pursue several objectives: providing social services with fewer state resources; co-opting organizations into behaving in accordance with state interests; pitting potential opposition factions against one another; and improving the state's image abroad while discrediting liberalism at home. While the Revolution in 2011 brought renewed hope for legal reform, it is unlikely that these state-civil society dynamics will change in the short term.
    Egypt; MALD thesis; Non-governmental organizations--Government policy
  - Reaching the Base of the Pyramid: An Analysis of Bakhresa Grain Milling Malawi's Inclusive Business Model, 2013-05; UA015.012.081.00010; Nagasaki, Tomohiro; A growing number of business leaders aspire to raise the well-being of poor populations in the developing world, while also generating profits, by pursuing "inclusive" business models. This thesis offers a description of the inclusive business model pursued by Bakhresa Grain Milling (Malawi) Ltd., and provides an analysis of how this company's outreach among microentrepreneurs (who sell wheat based snacks called mandasi) contributes to its own business success, and how it affects the lives of the entrepreneurs themselves. The research is based on interviews with company personnel, field interviews with microentrepreneurs selling various wheat based products, and secondary household survey data. This thesis suggests that even though the microentrepreneurs are two links in the value chain removed from direct dealings with the company, the company nonetheless recognizes that outreach among them increases the size of its market. While the outreach may increase profits for some microentrepreneurs, it also increases supply and drives down the price of mandasi. It may, therefore, leave some mandasi sellers worse off, while passing on benefits to mandasi consumers, many of whom are part of the base of the pyramid.
    MALD thesis; Entrepreneurship -- Developing countries; Microfinance.; Bakhresa Grain Milling (Malawi) Ltd
  - The Role of Memory in Post-Genocide Rwanda, 2013-06; UA015.012.081.00011; Conway-Gaffney, Katherine E.; Since the end of the 1994 Rwandan Genocide the Rwandan government and institutions within civil society have promulgated an official narrative of the events. This version of the narrative or "official memory" has tailored public remembrance and discourse, limiting the debate about the past. In present day Rwanda, controls exists that curtail open public remembrance, education, and conversations. The role of memory thus becomes a primary consideration in government, civil society, and in the social fabric of the Rwandan people. The government and social institutions control much of the collective memory, limiting discussions of ethnicity and events that took place outside of the specific time frame considered in the official memory. Limits to memory include restrictions on the freedom of speech, a focus on minimizing ethnic identity, methods of memorialization, and control over the versions of memory that are taught in schools, celebrated during the month of April, and discussed in public spaces. This thesis will assess the role of memory in guiding the current narrative of Rwandan society, institutions, and reconciliation ultimately addressing the friction caused in collective remembrance, identity, and social fabric. Subsequently, this thesis will address potential processes of engaging with memory in the present about the past that could include wider truth-telling and grappling with the historical record in order to shift a population towards deeper understanding, and potentially reconciliation, in both private and public spaces.
    Rwanda; MALD thesis; Collective memory--Rwanda; Rwanda--History--Civil War, 1990-1993
  - Technical Efficiency of Rice Production in India: A study using stochastic frontier analysis to estimate technical efficiency and its determinants, 2013-04; UA015.012.081.00012; Goldman, Dana Rose; This paper uses household survey data from the 2009 Kharif season in four states in India to estimate technical efficiency of rice production and analyze the determinants of technical efficiency. Technical efficiency scores and determinants of technical inefficiency were jointly estimated using a stochastic frontier analysis of production functions. The maximum likelihood approach in FRONTIER 4.1 was employed. On average, across the full sample (using a full-sample production frontier) farmers were operating with 52.89 percent efficiency. Farmers in Tamil Nadu were significantly more efficient than farmers in other areas (eastern Uttar Pradesh and Bihar/West Bengal). The number of years of formal education of the household head is positively and significantly correlated with technical inefficiency. Households with heads that are upper caste are significantly less efficient than households with non-upper caste heads. Households with concrete floors are significantly less efficient than that do not have them. Households that have a Below the Poverty Line card are significantly less efficient than those that do not have them. Households with access to piped water are significantly more efficient than those without access. The positive effects of formal education, caste and concrete floors on technical inefficiency are counter-intuitive results. Increased education, higher social status and increased household wealth would be expected to have a positive correlation with technical efficiency. A possible explanation may be that, better educated and higher caste households with more income own more land area and thus do not need to farm their land as intensively as households farming a smaller farm base. Alternatively, agriculture may not be the primary income generating activity for these households and thus they devote less time and managerial energy to agriculture. In order to increase technical efficiency in rice production, several policy goals have been identified. Because of the significant positive effect of fertilizer and pesticide use on output, increased fertilizer and pesticide use should be encouraged. In addition, due to the significant positive correlation between access to piped water and technical efficiency, increasing access to water infrastructure should be a priority. Given the high level of technical efficiency in Tamil Nadu, public investment in the state should be directed toward research and development for new technologies that will shift the production frontier outward. Lower degrees of technical efficiency in eastern Uttar Pradesh and Bihar/West Bengal mean that output growth can be achieved with current technology and thus public investment should be directed to measures that improve technical efficiency, such as training and infrastructure.
    India; MALD thesis; Agriculture; Industrial productivity
  - Participation, National Identity, Media & Technology in Greece, 2013; UA015.012.081.00013; Kaltsa, Panagiota; This work aims to set a framework for governments in crisis to strengthen their identity power and regain the trust of citizens, via participation and new communication technologies. The contribution of this thesis to existing literature is the introduction of electronic governance and citizen participation as a means to restore national identity in a market for loyalties, instead of regulation and control of the information flow. This work also introduces a comprehensive participation classification model and viral participation as a new academic term, which must be further researched. Based on the literature and field research on the development and promotion of participatory initiatives, a detailed participation communication strategy to achieve citizen engagement is suggested. Lastly, the business outline of a participatory initiative to address corruption in Greece is proposed and is subject to further modifications. ey words: national identity, regulation, participation, new communication technologies, traditional and new media, electronic governance, inclusion, control, collaboration, communication, corruption, telephony.
    Greece; MALD thesis; Social media; Nationalism; Political participation
  - Reconciliation Processes in Iraq. The Potential of Truth Commissions on Bringing Democracy, 2013-06; UA015.012.081.00014; Garcia, Ana; After many years of civil war and conflicts, Iraq is still currently involved in increased levels of sectarian violence. The American intervention in Iraq in 2003 and the more recent withdrawal of the international troops from the country have directly contributed to the crescent instability in the country. Achieving reconciliation within and between the different sectarian groups living in Iraq is missing. The implementation of a reconciliation process can bring not only knowledge and understanding about past crimes and violations of human rights committed, but also it can help building a new institutional democratic structure. In this regard, truth commissions on a national level have proven to be effective reconciliation instruments in contexts of grave violation of human rights, such as Iraq. Approaching a past history of violation of human rights with both the government and communities directly affected can have the potential to establish the bases for a long-term democratic system.
    Iraq; MALD thesis; Reconciliation; Iraq War, 2003-2011; Hussein, Saddam, 1937-2006
  - American Citizen Services: Consular Internship in Guadalajara, Mexico 2013, 2014; UA015.012.082.00001; Spielmann, Mary Chapman; This work describes the work involved in an internship in American Citizen Services in Guadalajara, Mexico over the summer of 2013, as well as analyzing the Mexican-American relationship and how it affects the services provided. The work focuses on immigration policies, theories of bureaucracy as well as economic, political, and familial ties.
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy.
    Mexico -- Relations -- United States.; United States -- Relations -- Mexico.; MALD thesis; Diplomatic and consular service -- Study and teaching (Internship) -- United States.; Diplomatic and consular service, American.; United States. Department of State -- Study and teaching (Internship)
  - Impact of Corporate Governance Practices on Financial Performance of Microfinance Institutions in India, 2014; UA015.012.082.00002; Durgavanshi, Siddharth S.; Corporate Governance practices of MFIs (Microfinance Institutions) across different economies have been known to affect the firm performance. This study explores the practices and key board features (Audit Committees, Independent Directors, International Directors, CEO-Board Chairman duality, Board Size and Director's Skills) that may have effect on the financial performance of "for profit" MFIs in India. The study identifies Board Size and presence of International Directors to have negative impact on the profitability of MFIs while the Directors" financial skills are found to have a positive impact on the profitability. No effect of CEO-Board Chairman dual role and audit committees was found on the MFI profitability.
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of International Business at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy.
    MIB thesis.; Microfinance -- India.; Financial services industry -- India.
  - Praeda Preda, Desuetude of a Gendered Code, 2014; UA015.012.082.00003; Houngbedji, Marlene M.; VICTIMS OF SEXUAL VIOLENCE: FROM SPOILS OF WAR TO FULL SUBJECTS OF INTERNATIONAL LAW Evolution of the Criminalization of War Time Rape from 1945 to the Present and the Gendered Perspective on Human Security. Women's legal status in times of war has historically been that of objects available to the conquering males; sexual violence perpetrated on those spoils of war (or in Latin, Praeda Preda) was a legitimate prerogative of the combatant and a victor's right. It was not until two major intra-state wars confounded the international community both by their intensity and their brutality that the latter's transformation into full subjects of international law occurred. This paper seeks to analyze the evolution of the legal status of victims of wartime sexual violence that has resulted from legal developments of the past twenty years. It explores their shift from objects to subjects of international law as having occurred within the context of the emergence of an individualized perspective on security. Contending that supranational criminal prosecution is crucial to preventing the systemic use of sexual violence in current and mostly intra-state conflicts, it also argues favor of the creation of an engendered human security paradigm informed by norms of refugee, human rights and humanitarian law as a legal tool against impunity.
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Masters of Law in International Law at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy
    LLM thesis.; Rape as a weapon of war.; War crimes.; Sex crimes (International law)
  - Turning the Lights Back On: Strategies for Private Participation in Electricity Infrastructure in Post-Conflict States, 2014; UA015.012.082.00004; Schwartz, Claudia L.; A comparative study of models to promote private participation in infrastructure, particularly electricity infrastructure, in post-conflict states, with a a focus on the case of Somaliland. The thesis combines a comprehensive literature review, a qualitative analysis of the specific context of Somaliland, and a quantitative analysis of the Somaliland energy sector using a capital budgeting financial model to assess profitability at different scales.
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Master of Arts in Law and Diplomacy at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy
    MALD thesis.; Electric power systems -- Protection.; Infrastructure (Economics) -- Security measures.
  - Exclusion and Agency in Rio de Janeiro: An Analysis of the Marginalization of Favela Residents and their Resistance to Violence, 2014; UA015.012.082.00005; Soltys, Gabrielle C.; Brazil has experienced a significant increase in political power and economic strength over the past decade, allowing a growing number of Brazilians to leave poverty and to enjoy higher living standards. However, this change has not affected all Brazilians equally, with millions still living in favelas and facing marginalization and stigmatization on a daily basis. This thesis begins by discussing the characteristics of favelas in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, and their residents and moves to analyze the causes of discrimination against favela residents, including race and gender, and the criminalization of individuals living in favelas. The thesis moves to explore violence in the public and private spheres in the favelas and the way in which the authorities use it as a justification for police operations to restore order in the favelas. It then discusses the growth of violent and organized crime in certain favelas, as well as the state's reaction via military police operations, women's police stations, and Pacifying Police Units, and its effectiveness at responding to violence. Finally, the thesis turns to the responses of favela residents and community organizations, and argues that these groups have had some success in attracting the attention of domestic and international audiences through the use of mainstream and social media, in raising awareness of incidents of police brutality and discrimination, and in obtaining a response from state authorities. However, the state still needs to fill many gaps in order to fully integrate favela residents into Brazilian society and to put an end to policies that exclude these individuals. Brazil's recent growth in political and economic power therefore represents an opportunity for the state to address its legacy of marginalization and discrimination and to formulate policies that will make the country more inclusive of all its citizens
    MALD thesis.; Squatter settlements -- Brazil -- Rio de Janeiro.; Slums -- Brazil -- Rio de Janeiro.; Violence -- Brazil -- Rio de Janeiro.; Poor -- Brazil -- Rio de Janeiro.; Violent crimes -- Social aspects -- Brazil -- Rio de Janeiro.
  - End of an era: why the erosion of petroleum's monopoly on fueling transportation should drive Saudi Arabia to raise output and lower prices, 2014; UA015.012.082.00006; Zoller, Drew E.; Due to the emergence of alternatives to petroleum as economically viable transportation fuels, the value of petroleum resources are likely to become threatened over time, and this paper proposes that the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia begin a long-term program to reduce the dominance of oil as its principal source of economic activity. With high oil prices making this difficult, it is believed that the Kingdom's long-term interest lies in proactively pushing oil prices down, in order to maximize long-term profits, reduce price volatility risks, and provide increasing incentives to government and private decision-makers to diversify the Kingdom's economy.
    Submitted in partial fulfillment of the degree Masters of Arts at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy.
    Petroleum industry and trade -- Saudi Arabia.; Petroleum industry and trade -- Saudi Arabia -- Forecasting.; Petroleum reserves -- Saudi Arabia.; MA thesis.